Guide to the Elbert Russell Papers, 1893 - 1968
Duke University. University Archives
Elbert Russell papers 1893 - 1968
Russell, Elbert, 1871-1951.
1.3 linear feet Extent: 1,000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Elbert Russell served as a Quaker historian, author, minister, and Dean of the Divinity School at Duke University from 1928 until 1941. Personal and professional papers contain correspondence, manuscript materials, sermons, articles and short writings, and clippings. Major subjects include Duke University Divinity School, study and teaching of the Bible, history of Quakerism, study and teaching of Quakerism, fellowship, study and teaching of pacifism, and sermons. Materials range in date from 1893-1968. English.
RL.01834
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Elbert Russell Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1966, 1968, and 1974.
Biographical Note
Elbert Russell, Quaker historian, author, minister, and leader, was born in 1871 in Friendsville, Tennessee. He was educated at Earlham College (Richmond, Ind.) and the University of Chicago. After earning a degree at the University of Chicago (Ph.D.), he returned to teach religion at Earlham College from 1895 to 1915. Russell also taught at Johns Hopkins University, Woolman College, Haverford College, and Swarthmore College.
Russell joined the faculty of the Duke University Divinity School in 1926 as a professor of Biblical Interpretation. In 1929, he became Dean of the Divinity School. He served on the Executive Committee of Carolina Institute of International Relations and worked closely with colleagues at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill to establish a network of specialists in nonviolent international relations. When he retired from the Divinity School in 1942, the Divinity School Alumni Association established the Elbert Russell Scholarship in his honor.
Russell was a prominent leader of the Society of Friends, or Quakers, a traditionally pacifist religious group. He was a guest speaker at Quaker educational institutions, a visiting preacher at churches and religious gatherings across the country, and a teacher of nonviolent conflict resolution. In 1927, he traveled to Central America in on a goodwill mission. After World War II, he traveled extensively in Europe, Asia, and the Middle East working on projects for his church and as a representative of the American Friends Services Committee. A pacifist, Russell had helped young men to defend their right to declare themselves conscientious objectors of war.
Some of Elbert Russell's writings include The Beatitudes (1929), The Book of Revelation: with an introduction, paraphrase and notes (1930), The Message of the Fourth Gospel (1932), A History of Quakerism (1942), and Elbert Russell, Quaker: an Autobiography (1956).
After retiring from Duke University in 1942, Russell and his family lived in Greensboro, N.C., Mobile, Ala., and St. Petersburg, Fla. Russell was married to Lieuetta Cox Russell, and had two children. Elbert Russell died in 1951 at age 80.
Collection Overview
Contains materials pertaining to the personal and professional work of Elbert Russell, Quaker historian, author, minister, and Dean of the Divinity School at Duke University from 1928 to 1941. In addition to his sermons, articles and books, Russell authored many poems and a play. Much of the correspondence in the collection includes references to pacifism and concerns sermons, teaching, preaching, Quakerism, and formal publication of his writings. Some clippings and correspondence in the collection date from after Russell's death and discuss his life and work. These most likely were collected by colleagues or family members. Materials range in date from 1893-1968.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Bible -- Homiletical use; Bible -- Study and teaching -- Sermons; Bible -- Study and teaching -- United States -- History; Clippings; Duke University. Divinity School; Duke University -- Faculty; Pacifism -- Religious aspects -- Society of Friends; Pacifism -- Societies, etc; Preaching -- United States; Quakers -- North Carolina; Quakers -- United States -- History; Russell, Elbert, 1871-1951; Sermons; Society of Friends -- United States -- History
Contents of Collection
- Container List:
  - Correspondence, 1924-February, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, March 1941-May 1941 (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, June 1941-1965 (Folder 3)
  - Articles and Sermons
    - Articles about politics, character, and the Bible, 1902-1934 (Folder 4)
    - Articles about trust, optimism, life problems, general issues, 1912-1951 (Folder 5)
    - The Inner Light in the History and Modern Problems of the Society of Friends, ca. 1945 (Folder 6)
    - The Basis of Authority in Religion, undated (Folder 7)
    - The Richmond Declaration of Faith, ca. 1922, 1961 (Folder 8)
      Includes correspondence.
    - The Relation of Christianity to War and Peace, ca. 1929 (Folder 9)
    - Criticism, correspondence, The Relation of Christianity to War and Peace, ca. 1929 (Folder 10)
    - Central American goodwill mission, 1927 (Folder 11)
    - Nonviolence as a Means of Social and Religious Progress, Freedom and Moral Responsibility in Modern Life, and Irish Stories, undated (Folder 12)
    - Learning and Piety, The Christian Church, Hero Worship, and meeting notes. (Folder 13)
    - King of Kings, The Little Girl God Forgot, Suspected Bigamy, Quaint Old Kernel of Kendal Green Fame, and a review of Gone with the Wind. (Folder 14)
    - Chapel Talks and More Chapel Talks (Folder 15)
      Includes some reprints.
    - The Importance of Religious Education, Courses in Religion for Negro Ministers, Why We Do Not Want County Liquor Stores, and Prohibition in America, undated (Folder 16)
  - Manuscript material for play about Antioch in Syria, A.D. 48, undated (Folder 17)
  - Sermons and prayers, 1937, undated (Folder 18)
  - The Seed Picker, 1926-1927 (Folder 19)
  - The Book of Revelation, [193-?] (Folder 20)
  - Poems, ca. 1893-1919 (Folder 21)
  - Tales of the Parson, part 1, ca. 1927-1928 (Folder 22)
  - Tales of the Parson, part 2, ca. 1927-1928 (Folder 23)
  - Articles on peace and nonviolence, undated (Folder 24)
  - Articles on Christianity, 1909-1951 (Folder 25-26)
  - Articles on Quakerism, 1897-1921 (Folder 27)
  - Articles on Quakerism and Present Tendencies, 1922-1951 (Folder 28-29)
  - A Commentary on the Book of Revelation, undated (Folder 30)
  - Clippings and reprints, ca. 1921-1951 (Folder 31)
  - Discussion of Russell's last lectures in North Carolina, 1968 (Folder 32)
Related Material
Divinity School records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Elbert Russell papers, 1895-1966.
Arthur and Kathleen Postle Archives and Friends Collection, Earlham College.